# **CRISTHIAN I. CASTRO ARIAS**

Mobile phone: +573114248799

Colombia







Data Scientist with experience in Python, SQL, data analysis, Machine Learning, Power BI, among other technologies. I have a background in chemical engineering and quality control that has helped me in the analysis and optimization of processes that occur in the data industry. I am a highly adaptable individual who is comfortable in different roles, willing to learn and unlearn. I have a conversational level in English and enjoy teamwork, sharing knowledge, asking for help and offering support when necessary.

#### **EDUCATION**

Bootcamp.	Soy Henry. Data Science, analysis and engineering	(2023 – Current)
Post-Bac.	Platzi. Data Science, analysis and engineering	(2022 – Current)
B. Sc.	Universidad del Valle. Ingeniería Química (2010 – 2015) Dissertation: "Morphology of Chars from Coal-Bagasse Mixtures in a Pyrolysis Process"	

#### **EXPERIENCE**

**Trapiche Lucerna**, Florida, Valle del Cauca **Junior Engineer**, Production Area

May 2020 to Jun 2020

- Supervised management indicator in clarification and evaporation areas.
- Elaborated process diagrams of the sugar mill.

Private Tutor, Bogotá Freelancer, Education

Jan 2017 to Sep 2018

• Prepared students in chemistry, mathematics and physics.

**Smurfit Kappa**, Yumbo, Valle del Cauca **Intern**, Technical and Quality Department

Mar 2015 to Sep 2015

- Executed GMP following local and international standards.
- Supervised sampling of final product and water involved in the process.

#### **PROJECTS**

# **Content-Based Movie Recommendation System**

Henry Bootcamp, Jun 2023 - Jul 2023

- Management and data cleaning of a dataset related to the film industry using Python libraries such as Pandas, NumPy and ast.
- Development of a recommendation model through vectorization, Scikit-Learn and algebraic processes such as cosine similarity.
- Deployment of the application with Render.com and an API built with FastApi.

# Morphology of chars from coal-bagasse mixtures in pyrolysis

University of Valle, Cali, Colombia, Aug 2014 - Sep 2015

- Grinding sugar cane bagasse and coal to get the samples of the research.
- Crafting disks made from mixtures of epoxy resin and particles of the grinded samples.
- Checking the disks through microscope and collect images of the chars belonging to mixtures of different proportions.
- Analyze the correlation between the shapes of the chars and properties of the samples like calorific value.

# PROFESSIONAL TRAINING AND COURSES

**Intermidiate Excel and Dashboards**, Platzi, 2023

Spark Fundamentals Platzi, 2023

MongoDB Fundamentals, Platzi, 2023

Docker, Platzi, 2023

Professional Python, Platzi, 2022

SQL and MySQL, Platzi, 2022

Database Building with MySQL, SENA, 2022

**Exploratory Data Analysis**, SENA, 2022

Advanced English, Colombian American Center, 2017

**HSEQ Training**, Future Builders, 2015

## **LANGUAGES**

**Spanish**: Native

English: Intermediate Speaker and Writer, Advanced Reading and Listener

French: Beginner

### **COMPUTER SKILLS**

Programming: Python, SQL, NOSQL, Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib.

Applications: VS Code, Office 365, Anaconda Suite, Hue, MySQL, PostregreSQL, Power

BI, Mongo Compass

Platforms: Windows, Linux